# Zhian N. Kamvar, PhD

1653 NW Midlake Ln Beaverton, OR 97006 # +1 (669) 210-4157 ⋈ zkamvar@gmail.com https://zkamvar.netlify.app Mastodon: @zkamvar@fosstodon.org

I am a highly-motivated software engineer of several published packages for population genetics/genomics, epidemiology, and reproducible publishing in R. As a domain expert in computational biology, software engineer, and a science communicator, I have both the specialist and generalist skillsets needed for efficient communication and collaboration between team members with diverse technical backgrounds. My goal in software development is to ensure that my applications are robust and accessible to researchers regardless of computational skills. Above all, I aim to ensure my software is usable, efficient, consistent, and correct through best practices in software development and reproducibility.

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

Project Highly experienced (10 years) in collaborative development with Git and GitHub; managing Management: projects, teams, and code review

10 years experience in developing well-tested and cross-disciplinary scientific software

Employs problem-forward approach to addressing researcher needs through iterative feedback

Developed an easy-to-use open source lesson infrastructure to build reproducible data science lessons

Coordinated communications to hundereds stakeholders in separate sub-communities about the impacts of the new infrastructure

Seamless roll out to >50 source repositories maintained by >100 volunteers for lessons that serve >10,000 learners annually

Languages: Expert R developer of several widely used R packages (10 years)

Experienced in creating unique Python 3 modules for population genomic simulation analysis pipeline (3 years)

Experienced in parsing structured text content in XPath and Lua (3 years)

Developed GitHub Actions to work with the GitHub (REST and GraphQL) API using BASH, R, and node JS (3 years)

Experience building reproducible analysis with CI and Docker (Kamvar, 2017)

Maintained reproducible pipelines in Make and BASH (2 years) for both continuous integration and HPC frameworks

Implemented recursive and bit-level operations in C to vastly improve speed of R code in the poppr package

Communication: Coached >100 graduate researchers to communicate their research to broad audiences in the award-winning radio program, Inspiration Dissemination (https://blogs.oregonstate. edu/inspiration)

> Developed and delivered material for 9 workshops in 3 disciplines that reached >300 people Published 19 peer-reviewed publications including 7 first-author publications

## SELECTED PROJECTS (ON GITHUB)

Workflows: carpentries/lesson-transition automated workflow to transform Carpentries-style lessons to

new infrastructure

R packages: carpentries/sandpaper user interface to reproducibly build and deploy data science lessons

> ropensci/tinkr transform markdown to XML and back again grunwaldlab/poppr analysis of populations with mixed reproductive modes

Analyses: everhartlab/sclerotinia-366 fully automated and reproducible analysis in Docker

> zkamvar/clonal-inference-simulations simulation-based analysis in Python, R, and BASH

## Collaborations

2021-Present Maintainer, the tinkr R package, rOpenSci.

Collaboration with Maëlle Salmon (original author) of rOpenSci to create a lightweight R package to parse and transform Markdown documents to XML. This has been used in **validation** of markdown elements and facilitating **automated human language translation**.

2018–2019 Lead Developer, R4Epis Project, Médecins Sans Frontières (Doctors Without Borders).

Collaborated with diverse team of developers and field epidemiologists to create a well-tested series of templates for automated outbreak and survey data analysis.

#### EMPLOYMENT

2020-Present Lesson Infrastructure Developer, The Carpentries.

Lead development and deployment of a modular infrastructure for building reproducible lessons to bring data science skills to researchers worldwide.

2018–2020 Research Softare Engineer, Imperial College London.

Developed well-tested R packages for field epidemiology and modelling

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 1 first-author)

2017–2018 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, *University of Nebraska-Lincoln*.

Population genetics of the white mold pathogen Scleortinia sclerotiorum

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 2 first-author)

2012–2016 Graduate Research Assistant, Oregon State University, (Dissertation Research).

Development and application of tools for genetic analysis of clonal populations

(9 peer-reviewed publications, 4 first-author)

# QUALIFICATIONS

2016 **Ph.D. Botany and Plant Pathology (3.65 GPA)**, *Oregon State University (OSU)*, Corvallis, OR, USA.

Dissertation: Development and Application of Tools for Analysis of Clonal Populations

2007 B.S. Biology, Truman State University (TSU), Kirksville, MO, USA.

## SELECTED PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS AND TALKS

• Kamvar ZN (2022) Building Accessible Lessons with R and Friends. rstudio::conf(2022): https://zkamvar.netlify.app/talk/carpentries-rstudio-2022/

• **Kamvar ZN**, Amaradasa BS, Jhala R, McCoy S, Steadman JR, Everhart SE. (2017) Population structure and phenotypic variation of *Sclerotinia sclerotiorum* from dry bean (*Phaseolus vulgaris*) in the United States. *PeerJ* **5**:e4152 doi: 10.7717/peerj.4152

data/analysis: https://github.com/everhartlab/sclerotinia-366

doi: 10.17605/OSF.IO/EJB5Y

### Personal References

#### Robert Davey (supervisor)

Director of Technology
The Carpentries
robertdavey@carpentries.org

## Kari L. Jordan (colleague, former supervisor)

Executive Director
The Carpentries
kariljordan@carpentries.org

#### François Michonneau (former colleage, former supervisor)

Senior Training Engineer Voltron Data francois.michonneau@gmail.com